A Finding Aid to the Billy Al Bengston Papers, circa 1940s-1989 (bulk 1960-1988), in the Archives of American Art AAA.bengbill
Archives of American Art
- Gallery and Museum Files, 1961-1989; Series 3; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 6-7
  - Linda Farris Gallery, 1981-1986 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Locksley Shea Gallery, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Los Angeles County Museum of Art, 1968-1970, 1980-1981 ,1983, 1988; (5 folders) (Box 7, Folder 16-20)
  - Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Lowe Art Museum, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Malibu Art and Design, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Malinda Wyatt Gallery, 1980-1983 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Margo Leavin Gallery, 1969-1974 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Martha Jackson Gallery, 1962, 1964-1969; (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 26-27)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Mirage Editions, 1981-1982, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - Mizuno Gallery, 1970-1980 (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - Multiples Inc., 1968-1973 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Municipal Art Gallery, Barnsdall, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Museum of Contemporary Art, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Rolf Nelson, 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Nicholas Wilder Gallery, 1972-1976 (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Oakland Museum, 1983, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Otis Art Institute, 1980, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Pace Gallery, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Pamela Auchincloss Gallery, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Pasadena Art Museum, circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Portland Center For Visual Arts, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Pyramid Galleries, 1974-1976 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Reese Paley Gallery, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Rhode Island School of Design, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Ronald Feldman Fine Arts, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Rosamund Felsen Gallery, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Ruth Schaffner Gallery, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - San Diego University, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 1976, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Santa Barbara Museum of Art, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Seder/Creigh Gallery, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Shoshana Wayne Gallery, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 53)
  - Signature Gallery, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 54)
  - Smith Anderson Gallery, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Texas Gallery, 1971-1984; (6 folders) (Box 7, Folder 56-61)
  - Thomas Babeor Gallery, 1980-1984; (4 folders) (Box 7, Folder 62-65)
  - Tortue Gallery, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - University of Houston, 1978, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - University of South Florida, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Utah Museum of Fine Arts, 1969-1970 (Box 7, Folder 69)
  - Vancouver Art Gallery, circa 1969 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1967, 1970s, 1981-1982 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Works Gallery, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 72)
- Teaching Records, 1968-1982; Series 4; 7 Folders Box 7
  Found here are scattered documents relating to Bengston's brief teaching career and lecture series at the University of California, Irvine, University of Colorado, and the Art Center of the College of Design. There is also one folder concerning the California Arts Council Master/Apprentice program and three folders of papers written by his students at University of California, Irvine.
  - Art Center College of Design, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - California Arts Council, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - University of California, Irvine, 1973; (4 folders) (Box 7, Folder 75-78)
  - University of Colorado, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 79)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1960-1987; Series 5; 1 Linear feet Boxes 7-8
  This series houses Bengton's personal business records documenting sales, loans, shipping, and the restoration of his artwork through correspondence, inventories, invoices, price lists, and receipts. Also found are records of sales and loans of artwork by others in his possession, and his representation of Paula Barton.
  Records of personal finances include purchase orders, insurance estimates, tax forms, utility bills, investment records, and grant applications to the Guggenheim Foundation and the National Endowment for the Arts.
  - Art Sales, circa 1960, 1968, 1970-1974; (6 folders) (Box 7, Folder 80-85)
  - Paula Barton, 1969-1972 (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Bill of Sale, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Brooke Alexander Inc., 1969-1984 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Check Fraud, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Consignment Sheets, 1968-1971 (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - Contracting, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - Damaged Artwork, 1966-1972 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Guggenheim Foundation, 1967-1971, 1975; (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 2-4)
  - House and Apartment Rentals, circa 1970s (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - IBM, 1978-1986 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Insurance, circa 1960s, 1974-1981 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Inventories, circa 1970, 1979-1983; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
  - Invoices, 1968-1975, 1980-1986; (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 10-12)
  - IOU, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Loans, 1966-1982, 1986-1987; (21 folders) (Box 8, Folder 14-34)
  - National Endowment For the Arts, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Pacific Interconnect, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - P.C. Associates, 1980-1986; (5 folders) (Box 8, Folder 37-41)
  - Personal Appearance Release, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Price Lists, circa 1960s-1980s; (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 43-44)
  - Purchases, 1970, 1972, 1979-1984; (3 folders) (Box 8, Folder 45-47)
  - PYTKA, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Shipping Receipts, 1979-1987; (4 folders) (Box 8, Folder 49-52)
  - Sprint, circa 1986 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Swim Swim, 1979-1981 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Tax Materials, 1973-1975 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - United Artists Ltd., 1971-1983 (Box 8, Folder 56)
- Project Files, 1968-1987; Series 6; 0.25 Linear feet Boxes 8-9
  This series includes scattered correspondence, agreements, floor plans, notes, and printed materials related to several of Bengston's commissions and projects. Projects include the book Business Cards with Ed Ruscha, work with Mexican weavers and ceramicists, and the construction of a studio in Hawaii. Commission files are found for artwork Bengston executed for various public buildings in California, including the California State Office Building and the Prestonwood Towne Center. Also found are files concerning Bengston's Zodiac series, work on posters for the 1984 Olympic Games and the Broadway, watercolors to raise money for Jerry Brown's 1982 gubenatorial campaign, and designs for the house of Roy and Carol Doumani. Also found are a few scattered miscellaneous files concerning an exhibition held at Bengston's studio and one at the Security Pacific Bank.
  Photographs related to projects and commissions are found in Series 10, Photographs.
  - Artist Studio Open House, 1973-1975 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Blankets, 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - The Broadway, 1981-1982 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Building Arts Production Company, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Business Cards, Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Business Cards, Financial Materials, 1968-1977 (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
  - Business Cards, Notes, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Business Cards, Printed Materials, 1968 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - California State Office Building, Long Beach, 1981-1983 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Doumani House, circa 1978-1984 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Exhibition Announcement Contest, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Hawaii Studio, circa 1979 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Houston Ballet, 1978-1979 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Institute of Experimental Printmaking, 1978-1985 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Irvine Hilton, 1984-1986; (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 14-15)
  - Los Angeles Institute of Contemporary Art, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Mexican Ceramics, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Olympic Poster, 1981-1983; (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 18-19)
  - Prestonwood Towne Center, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Scarf Design, 1977 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Security Pacific Bank Exhibition, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Sidecar, 1984-1985 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Venice Family Clinic, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Watercolors For Jerry Brown Campaign, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Zodiac, 1970s-1980s; (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 26-27)
- Writings, 1967-circa 1988; Series 7; 0.25 Linear feet Box 9, OV 1
  This series consists of writings by Bengston and others. Writings and notes by Bengston concern exhibitions of West Coast art, thoughts on being an artist and the artistic community in general, motorcycles, autobiographical essays, and a recollection of John Altoon. Also included are art survey questionnaires sent out by Bengston; respondents include Peter Alexander, Carl Andre, John Chamberlain, Dan Flavin, Joe Goode, Robert Graham, Roy Lichtenstein, John McCracken, Robert Motherwell, Ed Ruscha, Frank Stella, Peter Voulkos, and H.C. Westermann. Clippings of published articles by Bengston have been filed in this series.
  The bulk of the writings by others are essays written for exhibition catalogs. Also found are transcripts of interviews with Bengston, exhibition reviews, an article about the Doumani House project, essays about Bengston and his work, including one by Christopher Isherwood, and a proposed exhibition program by Walter Hopps, Robert Irwin, and Joshua Young.
  - Writings by Bengston (Box 9)
    - Artist's Survey, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Autobiographical Writings, circa 1968 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - "Grab Ass,", circa 1970s (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - "Late Fifties at Ferus,", 1969; (see also OV 1) (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - Letters of Recommendation, 1970, 1976, 1981, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - "Los Angeles Artists' Studios,", 1970 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - On Artistic Community, 1960s (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - On John Altoon, circa 1969 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - On Motorcycles, circa 1970s (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - On "West Coast: 1945-1969" at the Pasadena Art Museum, circa 1970 (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - "The Revolution and Invelopment of California Art in California,", late 1960s (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - "Sequential Order For Artistic Downfall,", late 1970s (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - Writings by Others (Box 9)
    - [Biographical Sketch and Exhibition List], 1979 (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - [Copy For New Works In Clay Catalog], 1976 (Box 9, Folder 41)
    - [Doumani House], circa 1982 (Box 9, Folder 42)
    - "A Remembrance of the Emerging Los Angeles Art Scene," by Henry Hopkins, circa 1988 (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - "Artist's Dialogue: a Conversation With Billy Al Bengston," by Fredericka Hunter, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 44)
    - [On Bengston's Paintings] by Christopher Isherwood, circa 1976 (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - "Interview With Billy Al Bengston" by Andrea Leavin, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 46)
    - "Billy Al Bengston: Some Retrospective Thoughts" by Jane Livingston, circa 1988 (Box 9, Folder 47)
    - [Introduction to Billy Al Bengston: Watercolors 1974-1980] by Jane Livingston, circa 1981 (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - "Billy Al Bengston, For Example" by Jeff Perrone, circa 1981 (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - "Billy Al Bengston: New Paintings" by Peter Plagens, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - "Preface [to Billy Al Bengston: Paintings of Three Decades]" by Linda Cathcart and Christina Orr-Cahall, circa 1988 (Box 9, Folder 51)
    - "Proposal For Exhibition Program" by Walter Hopps, Robert Irwin, and Joshua Young, circa 1970s (Box 9, Folder 52)
    - [Biographical Sketch] by Allan Shean, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 53)
    - "Painting As a Visual Diary" by Karen Tsujimoto, circa 1987; (2 folders) (Box 9, Folder 54-55)
    - "The Installation of Billy Al Bengston at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art" by Maurice Tuchman, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 56)
    - Unidentified Manuscript, 1960s (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - "Late Fifties at Ferus,", 1969; (see also Box 9, F31) (Box OV 1)
- Artwork, 1960s-1987; Series 8; 7 Folders Box 9
  This series consists mainly of artwork created by Bengston for projects and commissions, including sketches for the Building Arts Company, Prestonwood Towne Center, and Sidecar lamp projects, and drawings for the Zodiac project. Also included are drawings of frames and paintings, two watercolors, and doodles.
  - Drawings, 1960s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - Drawings For Zodiac Project, 1970s-1980s (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Print, circa 1978-1982 (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - Sketches For Building Arts Production Company Project, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Sketches For Prestonwood Towne Center, circa 1977 (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - Sketches of Lamps For Sidecar, 1984 (Box 9, Folder 63)
  - Watercolors, 1970s-1980s (Box 9, Folder 64)
- Printed Materials, 1958-1988; Series 9; 1.25 Linear feet Boxes 9-10, OV 1-2
  This series includes clippings, exhibition announcements, exhibition catalogs, posters, press releases, and reproductions of artwork. Clippings are about Bengston, reviews of group and solo exhibitions, articles about southern California art and culture, and coverage of art and social events. The majority of exhibition catalogs are for group exhibitions, while exhibition announcements include both solo and group shows. Also included are advertisements, product catalogs, bus schedules, and athletic and outdoor club brochures collected for Bengston's personal use. Of interest is a poster for Bengston's first exhibition in 1956, the exhibition catalog for Bengston's first solo exhibition in 1958, a poster for a 1962 exhibition autographed by Buster Keaton, and the exhibition catalog designed by Ed Ruscha for Bengston's 1968 retrospective at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art.
  - Advertisements, circa 1981 (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Biographical Sketch, circa 1978 (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Book Catalog, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 67)
  - Catalog of Exhibitions, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Catalogs, 1985 and circa 1980s (Box 9, Folder 69)
  - Clippings (Box 9)
    - Articles About Bengston, 1968-1975, 1977-1985; (3 folders) (Box 9, Folder 70-72)
    - General Clippings, 1962-1964, 1966-1988; (22 folders; see also OV 1) (Box 9, Folder 73-94)
    - Reviews and Notices, 1962, 1968-1988; (18 folders; see also OV 1-2) (Box 10, Folder 1-18)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1959, 1970-1984, 1988; (3 folders) (Box 10, Folder 19-21)
  - Catalogs, 1958, 1966, 1968, 1972, 1974, 1976-1977, 1979, 1981-1984; (5 folders) (Box 10, Folder 22-26)
  - Exhibition Flyers, circa 1969 (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Furniture Advertisements and Catalogs, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Hawaii Materials, circa 1976 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Invitations, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Los Angeles Children's Museum, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 31)
  - Maps, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Postcards, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Posters, 1969-1970, 1973, 1975-1976, 1978-1983; (3 folders; see also OV 2) (Box 10, Folder 34-36)
  - Press Releases, 1968-1969, 1971-1972, 1976-1978, 1982, 1984, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 37)
  - Reproductions of Art Work, 1970s-1980s (Box 10, Folder 38)
  - Running Seminar Brochure, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - General Clippings, 1964, 1966, 1971, 1974; (see also Box 9, F73-94) (Box OV 1)
  - Reviews and Notices, 1965, 1967-1968; (see also Box 10, F1-18) (Box OV 1)
  - Reviews and Notices, 1971, 1973, 1975, 1978-1979; (see also Box 10, F1-18) (Box OV 2)
  - Posters, 1956, 1960-1962, 1988; (see also Box 10, F34-36) (Box OV 2)
- Photographs, circa 1940s-1987; Series 10; 0.5 Linear feet Box 10
  Photographs are of Bengston, his friends, galleries, exhibitions, sites of Bengston's commissions, and one family photograph dating from the 1940s. Photographs of other artists include Carlos Almaraz, Richard Diebenkorn, David Hockney, Garry Winogrand. Also included are photographs of artwork, including the Plato de Moreno series of watercolors commissioned in 1982 by Jerry Brown's gubernatorial campaign. Photocopies of photographs not found elsewhere have been kept. Of interest are photographs of Bengston during his 1975 residency at the Everson Museum of Art, helping to construct the house of Roy and Carol Doumani, and Bengston conversing with Buck Henry.
  Also found are slides of Bengston's artwork for the installation of his 1988 retrospective.
  - Artists, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 40)
    Found are photographs of Carlos Almaraz, Richard Diebenkorn, David Hockney, Garry Winogrand.
  - Artwork, 1961, 1968, 1969, 1975-1976, 1980-1983, 1986, and undated; (11 folders) (Box 10, Folder 41-51)
  - Artwork By Others, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 52)
    Found are photographs of artwork by Father Lee Lubbers
  - Billy Al Bengston, circa 1940s, 1975, 1981-1982 (Box 10, Folder 53)
  - Billy Al Bengston (Photocopies), 1959, 1970s (Box 10, Folder 54)
  - Billboard, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 55)
  - California State Office Building, Long Beach, circa 1982 (Box 10, Folder 56)
  - Damaged Artwork, 1969, 1970s (Box 10, Folder 57)
  - Doumani House, circa 1978-1980 (Box 10, Folder 58)
  - Fredericka Hunter and Ian Glennie, circa 1978 (Box 10, Folder 59)
  - Galleries, 1969, 1978, 1983, 1987; (2 folders) (Box 10, Folder 60-61)
  - Installation of Artwork, 1970s (Box 10, Folder 62)
  - Institute of Experimental Printmaking, circa 1978-1982 (Box 10, Folder 63)
    Found are photographs of Sam Francis
  - Irvine Hilton Project, circa 1985-1986 (Box 10, Folder 64)
  - Hans Neuendorf, 1960s-1970s (Box 10, Folder 65)
  - Justyn Notcek, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 66)
  - Mexico, circa 1978 (Box 10, Folder 67)
  - Olympic Posters, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 68)
  - Prestonwood Towne Center Project, circa 1977 (Box 10, Folder 69)
  - Transparency, 1970s (Box 10, Folder 70)
  - Unknown Girl, circa 1960s (Box 10, Folder 71)
  - Slides (Box 10)
    - Artwork, 1971-1972 (Box 10, Folder 72)
    - Artwork, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 73)
    - Artwork, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 74)
    - Artwork, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 75)
    - Artwork, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 76)
    - Artwork, 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 77)
    - Artwork, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 78)
    - Artwork, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 79)
    - Artwork, 1981 (Box 10, Folder 80)
    - Artwork, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 81)
    - Artwork, 1983 (Box 10, Folder 82)
    - Artwork, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 83)
    - Artwork, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 84)
    - Undated Artwork, 1970s-1980s (Box 10, Folder 85)
    - Illustrations For Unknown Publication, circa 1977 (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - Installation of "Billy Al Bengston: Paintings of Three Decades" at the Contemporary Arts Museum, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 87)
    - Installation of "Billy Al Bengston: Paintings of Three Decades" at the Oakland Museum, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 88)
    - Installation of "Billy Al Bengston: Paintings of Three Decades" at the Contemporary Museum of Art, Honolulu [?], 1988-1989 (Box 10, Folder 89)
    - Building Arts Project, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 90)
    - California State Office Building, Long Beach, 1981-1983 (Box 10, Folder 91)
    - Institute of Experimental Printmaking, 1978-1985 (Box 10, Folder 92)
    - Irvine Hilton, 1984-1986 (Box 10, Folder 93)